<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Damnable principle of the Jesuites touching the murdering of Kings fully laid open in two eminent instances, de facto, by their own confession</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13687500</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13687500</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101373</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36075)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101373)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Damnable principle of the Jesuites touching the murdering of Kings fully laid open in two eminent instances, de facto, by their own confession</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Bowtel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes "The Jesuits ghostly wayes" and "The treason of Edw. Squire."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parry, William, d. 1585.</term>
               <term>Squire, Edward, d. 1598.</term>
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101373:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Damnable Principle OF THE JESUITES Touching the MURDERING OF KINGS: Fully laid open in Two Eminent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances <hi>de facto,</hi> by their own Confeſsion.</p>
            <q>As troops of Robbers wait for a Man, ſo the Company of Prieſts murder in the way by Conſent, <bibl>Hoſea 6.9.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Bowtel,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Star</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101373:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101373:2"/>
            <head>THE JESUITES Ghoſtly Wayes, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>BEfore the Advent of Jeſuites (ſaies <hi>France</hi> of their Catholick Church) we never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood what it was to deſtroy Kings and Princes. That is a Merchandiſe indeed too horrid for any Chriſtian people to deal in, but yet it ſeems not ſo bad, as to deter Jeſuites from having to do with it. And as it firſt of all came out of their ſhops by that wicked Vow of blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which they made to their Superiours, ſo they dearly love ſtill to keep up that traffick, becauſe of the no ſmall gain it brings in to them here, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101373:3"/>they are the abſolute lovers of this world,) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, like Paper and Packthread, Heaven when they tramp out of this life, is thrown in to the bargain, and given them as the laſt Recompence of all their Meritorious Deeds and Services: ſo that now Kings and Princes ſeem to hold the tenure of their lives at the will of two Landlords, God, and the Jeſuites, and either of them may turn them out of Poſſeſſion whenſoever they think fit.</p>
            <p>I have made choice of theſe two enſuing Stories, being, I think, as remarkable as almoſt any in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, (and there are not a few) to ſhow you how bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily they are bent both in their Natures and by their Function, againſt all that are not of the ſame dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Faith with them; not ſparing even ſo much as ſacred Majeſty, for whom they ought to have a continual Reverence and Dread, as being the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Seals of Gods more immediate impreſs of himſelf, eſpecially too, when he has ſo ſtrictly charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us all not ſo much as to touch his Anointed, that is, not to do them the leaſt hurt or prejudice, no, not even in our thoughts, and certainly then much leſs to come near them with blood-thirſty and violent hands.</p>
            <p>He who made the <hi>Humble Remonſtrance</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> to the then <hi>French</hi> King, being extreamly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to make it appear that the Jeſuites were moſt Calumniouſly accuſed of having attempted againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> life of the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> ſaies thus: <hi>As for the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>thoſe who have writ the truth, have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101373:3"/>teſtified our fidelity, and have not dared, to accuſe us of attempting any thing againſt the Queen in her eſtate: and thoſe who would fain calumniate us, know not how to fix their lyes and forgeries upon any of our deportments, by any probable Reaſon of truth.</hi> But however I will make it out that that Jeſuite is a Second <hi>Herodotus:</hi> and I confer no flight and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial honour on him, when I compare him to that great perſon, who 'tis thought, was the father, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the lying and fabulous Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Parry,</hi> Doctor of the Civil Law, a man of ſmart parts, but as it is ſaid of him, of profuſe waſtfulneſs, ryot,<note place="margin">Speed's Chron. in Q. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz. an. Dom. <hi>1584.</hi> f. <hi>1157.94.</hi>
               </note> and prodigality, after he had eat and drank out his own eſtate, and conſumed the greateſt part of his two widows for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; and wounded his creditor, <hi>Hugh Hare,</hi> a Gentleman of the Temple, by committing bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glary; for which fact he was condemned to dye, but by the compaſſion and tenderneſs of the Queen, upon his ſuing for it, got his reprieve of life: he was deliberating with himſelf what courſe to take, and at laſt reſolved to fly his Countrey, and to ſail for <hi>France.</hi> And being got to the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> and deſirous to ſcrew himſelf into a familiarity with ſome Engliſh Gentlemen, fugitives likewiſe from their own Countrey, for the ſake of their Religion; they were ſomewhat ſhie at firſt how they entertained him, not knowing but that he might come expreſly to them to ſpy out their actions; which made them ſend him to <hi>Lyons,</hi> and afterwards to <hi>Venice;</hi> where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101373:4"/>an Engliſh-man, he was put to the Inquiſition: But he gave ſo good an Account of his Catholick Religion, that his Judges thought it their duty to ſend him back; being well beloved by all the Catholicks, and by Father <hi>Benedicto Palmio,</hi> a Jeſuite of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation among them, he took up a helliſh reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to fall from his natural allegiance, and wholly to devote himſelf to the intereſts of the See of <hi>Rome:</hi> and to confirm this abſolutely to them, he projected to kill the Queen, and by the ſame means to ſet fire to the four corners of <hi>England:</hi> grounding this his enterprize here, both to deliver his Countrey from the tyranny under which it groaned, and to advance to the Crown the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> a Catholick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, who had lately married Prince Dauphine, and who (laying her title from <hi>Margaret<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the eldeſt daughter of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, linked in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with <hi>James</hi> the fourth King of that name; ſhe being the daughter of King <hi>James</hi> the fifth, his ſon,) was the neareſt in blood, and the lawful heir to the crown of <hi>England.</hi> An opinion that came from his own inſtinct, without ever having before his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture communicated it to the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> as ſince he confeſſed in the priſon. But becauſe this enterprize was ſomewhat arduous and difficult, and his conſcience was not ſo ſtiffed, but that it gave him now and then bitter remorſes, he went to confer about it with <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio,</hi> who according to the common maxime of his ſect, not only did not diſſuade him from it, but greatly confirmed him in it, and told him that in ſuch a matter as that was, only length of time could be prejudicial. Whereupon he packs away again to <hi>Lyons,</hi> and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101373:4"/>his deſign to the Jeſuites, he is mightily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and honoured by them. Some little time after he returns to <hi>Paris,</hi> where ſome Engliſh Gentlemen fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives being acquainted with his intention, began to imbrace, and hug him in their arms: among the reſt one <hi>Thomas Morgan,</hi> who aſſured him that within a ſhort time after he ſhould be in <hi>England,</hi> and ſhould have executed his buſineſs, he would give order for a puiſſant army of <hi>Scots</hi> to come thither, to ſecure the Kingdom to the Queen of <hi>Scots.</hi> Now although <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſeemed to be reſolved on all things, yet he could not ſometimes keep out the ſtings that gnawed and tore his conſcience. And therefore he communicated it to ſome perſons of the Engliſh Church, all of whom diſſwaded him from it: eſpecially a learned Prieſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Watell,</hi> who wiſely remonſtrated to him, that all the rules of God, and of the world were repugnant and contrary to that his deliberation. In ſo great an irreſolution, he reſolves to inquire, and take advice of the Jeſuites of <hi>Paris,</hi> among whom he addreſſes himſelf to father <hi>Hannibal Coldretto,</hi> to whom he diſcourſed in confeſſion, his firſt intention, and the incertainty and diſquiet into which <hi>Watel</hi> had redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him. But the Jeſuite who never wanted perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive reaſons to urge on ſuch a wickedneſs, affirmed to him that <hi>Watel,</hi> and all others who went about to fill his ſoul with ſuch kind of frivolous ſcruples, were Hereticks. And having ſet all things to rights again, made him, according to their uſual manner, receive the communion with ſome other Lords. <hi>Parry</hi> being fully ſatisfied now in his mind, takes his leave of them, and comes back for <hi>England,</hi> reſolved to put
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101373:5"/>his Treaſon into effect. The better to accompliſh which, he ſought out all the ways he could think of to get to kiſs the Queens hand; ſaying he had ſomething to communicate to her Majeſty of very great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and which he could deliver to none but her ſelf. This was about <hi>February,</hi> in the year 1583. And in ſhort, at the laſt he got himſelf introduced into her preſence, he diſcourſed to her in full length the particularities of his voyage, and how counterfeiting himſelf to be a fugitive, he had made a diſcovery of all the practices and conſpiracies which the Engliſh Catholicks had contrived againſt her Majeſty: and alſo that he had promiſed them to be the firſt that ſhould undertake her death: which had gained him great credit among them. But for all that, he would ſooner chooſe a thouſand tortures than ſully his ſoul with ſo damnable a thought. He was a man of good Oratory, and could deliver himſelf excellently well upon any thing; of a fine, graceful preſence; and who was prepared beforehand with all things which he ſhould have to ſay to her. The Queen, who did not want ſpies, knew very well that one part of his ſtory was true enough; which made her give the more credit to all the reſt. She gave him the honour to be near her perſon, and commanded him not to go out of her Court, but in the mean time try to feel the pulſe of her enemies by his inſinuating letters. All this he promiſed to do with the greateſt faithfulneſs in the world; and upon thoſe promiſes, feeding that Princeſs with lyes, he often had the priviledge of her ear. One day ſhe being a hunting with ſome Ladies, he follow'd her cloſe, without ever ſuffering his eye
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101373:5"/>to loſe ſight of her, and as ſhe was got a pretty way off from her company, having light off her Horſe a little to refreſh herſelf at the foot of a Tree, in a Wood; <hi>Parry</hi> being near her, was twice in the mind to have killed her, but he was hindered at that time through the thoughts and proſpect of the frequent privacy ſhe permitted him to have with her. Another time walking with her after ſupper, in the garden of her Palace called <hi>White-hall,</hi> which is next to the <hi>Thames,</hi> where he had a Boat waiting on him, to ſave himſelf after he had given the fatal blow, as he ſought his opportunity, the Queen gave him the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, after the manner you ſhall now hear: He thought to have done his buſineſs within a little time after, it beginning then to grow duskiſh, and when he had got her down to the bottom of the Garden, then to murder her; but ſhe was from that time making up towards her Palace, telling him that it was high time for her to be in her Chamber, being afraid of blaſts, and that ſhe was the next morning early to be let blood by the advice of her Phyſicians: and withal laughing ſaid, that they would not take ſo much blood away from her, as many in the world deſired they ſhould: at theſe words ſhe withdraws, leaving <hi>Parry</hi> in a great aſtoniſhment and confuſion in having let ſlip ſo fair an opportunity and conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for him to perform his bloody and damnable deſign.</p>
            <p>Now as carried himſelf after this manner to the Queen, imagining he ſtood in need of a confident to ſecond him, he addreſſed himſelf to one <hi>Edmund Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101373:6"/>his friend, a worthy Gentleman, who ſuffered in the afflictions of <hi>England,</hi> for his Religion, whom he went often to viſit; and after he had made him ſolemnly ſwear upon the Holy Goſpel, not to reveal a word of what he ſhould tell him, he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to him by little and little his intention; and the ſumm, if he would be one with him, of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy; and how that he had as much reaſon as moſt people to reſent the injuries which had been done him in particular: and that it was the true and only means of re-eſtabliſhing the Catholick Religion in <hi>England,</hi> as alſo to eſtabliſh the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> there too. That in doing ſo good a deed they ſhould both have a pretty large ſhare in the ſpoyl. <hi>Nevill</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able well to digeſt that new counſel; <hi>Parry</hi> ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him if he had never read the book of Father <hi>Allen,</hi> which animated his reſolutions, and every word of which was a warrant for his prepared mind; and every line taught that Kings might be deprived, excommunicated, and violently depoſed in caſe of the Religion of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that civil wars upon that ſacred account were honourable. <hi>I have,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>a very eaſie acceſs to the Queen, as alſo you may have as ſoon as you will make your ſelf known at Court. After we ſhall have given the fatal blow, we will ſlip our ſelves into a boat which I have continually waiting on me at the ſtairs, and from thence we will get into ſome Veſſel that will then be putting out to ſea: This is a thing which we may both do upon my honour, without the leaſt diſturbance. Nevill</hi> ſtill entertaining him with fair promiſes, but yet without abſolutely giving him an, aſſurance that he would do it, or a flat denyal that he would not.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101373:6"/>In ſhort, he thought it was not ſafe for him any longer to delay the time without advertiſing the Queen of it, to whom the eighth day of <hi>Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 1584. he related all that had paſſed between him and <hi>Parry,</hi> who was then at Supper with the Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> The Queen; extreamly ſurprized commanded <hi>Walſingham,</hi> her chief Secretary of State, to apprehend them both, but however to treat mildly with <hi>Parry,</hi> to ſee if peradventure he could get out the truth from him: which he did, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating to him how that the Queen had received ſome hew Intelligence of a Conſpiracy againſt her. And becauſe the Malecontents had ſome confidence in him, he deſired him to tell him if he had heard nothing of it. Two or three times being interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon that matter, he ſaid he had never heard one ſyllable of it. If he had confeſſed the Intrigue between him and <hi>Nevil,</hi> and for an excuſe had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that what he had done was purely through diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, and by way of diſſimulation, and he had only made uſe of that trick to ſound the Opinions of thoſe who concealed a diſcontent in their ſouls, <hi>Walſingham</hi> ſaid ſince to ſeveral perſons that he would have been abſolutely acquitted. But having ſo peremptorily denyed it, he then laid before him the depoſition of <hi>Nevil,</hi> which put him into great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and aſtoniſhment, which obliged the Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to make him his gueſt for that night. Then next morning early <hi>Parry</hi> went to wait upon him in his Chamber, and told him that he remembred he had held ſome diſcourſe with <hi>Nevil</hi> touching a point of Doctrine contained in the Anſwer made to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101373:7"/>Book Intituled, <hi>The Execution of Juſtice in England,</hi> in which it was proved, that for the Advancement of the Catholick Religion, it was lawful to take away the life of a Prince: but that as to him, he had never ſpoken a word of any deſign againſt the Queen. But yet <hi>Parry</hi> and <hi>Nevil</hi> are ſent to two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Priſons, with interdiction to their Keepers not to let any whoſoever to come near either of them, but thoſe the Queen ſhall appoint. The former for having concealed ſix Months and above, this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy; the other for the Treaſon, whereof he was charged and accuſed. Both of them are interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and afterwards upon requeſt made to them gave their Confeſſions in writing, <hi>Nevil</hi> the tenth of <hi>February, Parry</hi> the eleventh, and the thirteenth. That of <hi>Nevil</hi> containing the ſubornations and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits of <hi>Parry</hi> to the utmoſt of his power: that of <hi>Parry,</hi> how he had at firſt projected this Treaſon in <hi>Venice,</hi> incouraged to it by the exhortations of the Jeſuite <hi>Palmio:</hi> afterwards confirmed by the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites of <hi>Lyons,</hi> and laſt of all poſitively concluded on by the inſtigations of <hi>Hannibal Coldretto,</hi> and other Jeſuites of <hi>Paris,</hi> whereupon that devotion he had been firſt confeſſed, and afterwards he received the Communion. And it is a thing which methinks ought not to be buried in ſilence, that being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated by his Judges, he confeſſed that when he firſt of all diſcourſed with the Queen about the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies which the Fugitive Catholicks contrived againſt her, to be re-inſtated in their houſes; ſhe made him anſwer, that her Opinion had never obliged h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to treat any perſon ill for Religion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101373:7"/>unleſs under that colour and pretence, they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to attempt againſt her, and her Kingdom: and that for the future none ſhould be puniſhed for holding the Supremacy of the Pope, ſo long as they behaved themſelves like good and faithful Subjects. <hi>Nevil</hi> being re-examined and brought face to face to <hi>Parry,</hi> perſiſted firmly in his depoſition. But it was a thing abſolutely ſuperfluous and needleſs: for <hi>Parry</hi> had ſufficiently confeſſed it, alſo there were found in his houſe ſeveral Miſſives, Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Memorials that condemned him. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe during his impriſonment, he wrote Letters to the Queen, by which he moſt humbly intreated her to be pleaſed to pardon the fault, but not the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty he deſerved. He had for his Judges Sir <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Wray</hi> Knight, Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Speeds Chron. f. <hi>1158.</hi> n. <hi>99.</hi> Parries Letter to the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</note> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lords appointed for that purpoſe, who made him to come from the Priſon to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there being again interrogated in the preſence of all the people, he confeſſed the Treaſon. Alſo his precedent confeſſions were read before him, his miſſives that were ſent to him for that effect; and other pieces which were any wayes ſerviceable, for the clearer proving of the crime: adding that there was not any Conſpiracy ſince the firſt year of the Queens Reign, as touching Religion, in which he was not concerned, excepting that of the <hi>Agnus Dei;</hi> and that beſides that he had ſet down his Opinion in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, concerning the Succeſſor of the Crown, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the people to Rebellion. This criminal Cauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101373:8"/>was in hearing from the eighth of <hi>February</hi> 1584. unto the five and twentieth. On which day <hi>Parry</hi> was condemned to be hanged by the Neck, and that the rope ſhould be preſently cut, and he ſhould be Bowelled, to have his Entrails flung into the fire, and burnt before his eyes, afterwards to have his Head cut off, and his Body ſet at four quarters of the Town: and that from the Priſon he ſhould be drawn on a Sledge through the City of <hi>London</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place of Execution. That Sentence was then pronounced, but yet not immediately Executed. The ſecond of <hi>March, Parry</hi> was put into the hands of the Executioner. He, being advertiſed of this by the Sheriffes of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Middleſex,</hi> as if he were going to his Nuptials, and to meet at the place of his Execution the Miſtris of his deareſt Vows, dreſſed himſelf up in a long morning Gown of black Damask, and put about the neckband of his Shirt a great ſtarched Ruff, ſuch as was then wore, and in faſhion. And taking his leave of the other Priſoners, with a ſmooth and pleaſant coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, he made a Preſent to the Goaler of a Ring in which was ſet in Gold a rich Diamond, with theſe words, <hi>That he was very ſorry he was not in a capacity of gratifying him better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After that he was drawn upon a Sledge, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving mounted the Ladder, it is reported he prayed the Executioner, putting the Rope about his neck himſelf, not to rumple and diſorder his Ruff. Thus dyed that great Martyr of the Jeſuites, to be ſure not promiſing to himſelf any thing leſs than a Celeſtial
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101373:8"/>Paradiſe, for ſo deteſtable an enterpriſe in it ſelf, though ſet out to himſelf as Sacred, and as Meritorious a piece of Service as almoſt was poſſible to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. So worthy was it, that <hi>Raggazzoni</hi> the Pope's Nuntio promiſed him, ſo Catholick and pious an undertaking ſhould not be forgot at their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars; and ſo Meritorious, as that it did not only find his Holineſs his appprobation, but it ſtirred up the Pope to give him readily, and as it were by divine commiſſion the Abſolution of all his ſins, upon the firſt ſolicitation of Cardinal <hi>Como.</hi> And becauſe the Letter does come in here ſo pat to the purpoſe, methinks I cannot in Juſtice deny you the ſeeing of it, as it is Tranſlated from the Original Italian, and inſerted in <hi>Speeds Chron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In loc. qu. ſup.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101373:9"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Cardinal <hi>Como</hi>'s Letter to <hi>Parry.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SIr, His Holineſs hath ſeen your Letter of the firſt, with the Aſſurance included, and cannot but commend the good diſpoſition and Reſolution, which you write to hold towards the Service of the Church, and publick benefit: wherein his Holineſs doth exhort you to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, with cauſing to be brought to effect that which you promiſe. And to the end you may be ſo much the more enabled by that good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which hath moved you thereunto, his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs doth grant you Plenary Indulgence, and Remiſsion of all your ſins, according to your requeſt. Aſſuring you that beſides the merit that you ſhall receive therefore in Heaven, his Holineſs will further make himſelf debtor to acknowledge and requite your deſervings by all the beſt means he may. And that ſo much the more, in that you uſe the more modeſty, in not pretending any thing. Put therefore into effect your holy and honourable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101373:9"/>determinations, and attend your health. And, to conclude, I offer my ſelf unto you hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with all good and happy ſucceſs,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From <hi>Rome</hi> 
                        <date>the xxx. of <hi>January,</hi> 1584.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>At your diſpoſing, <hi>N.</hi> Card. <hi>de Como.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>BUt you ſhall now hear another worſe Tragedy acted againſt the ſame Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Queen, which was an Aſſaſſinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on purchaſed in the Year 1597. by the Jeſuites.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101373:10"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101373:10"/>
            <head>THE TREASON OF Edw. Squire.</head>
            <p>THe Miracle of the Jeſuites doubtleſs was great in the Converſion of <hi>Parry,</hi> but however it was not ſo great, nor of the ſame ſtuff with this I am now going to ſhow you. For <hi>Parry</hi> by his laſt Confeſſion acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he had had a hand in all the Conſpiracies form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Queen, and for Religion, but in one. But this Gentleman, whoſe horrid Treaſon I am
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101373:11"/>now to ſpeak of, had alwaies been of the Proteſtant Religion, and yet notwithſtanding by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite was not only brought over to that of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Catholick, but alſo was wrought upon to kill the Queen. And I do not queſtion but if that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe had took effect as they had deſigned, it would have been Meritorious enough, to be added to that Book of Miracles compoſed by <hi>Lewis Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheome,</hi> of the company of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>It was the laſt publick attempt that was made of taking away the Queens life; and it was by one <hi>Edward Squire</hi> a Scrivener living at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> who by Depu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation was imployed as Purveyor in the Queen's Stable; but hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wit being ſuperiour to that of his calling, and not being content with the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his Fortune, he put himſelf in the Year 1595. into the Fleet of Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> who was taking his laſt Voyage into the <hi>Indies.</hi> The Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, which this <hi>Squire</hi> was in being ſmall, happened to be driven away by the weather, and loſt ſight of the Fleet, and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong after was taken near <hi>Guadalupe</hi> by five <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Frigats, and he with the reſt was brought a Priſoner into <hi>Spain,</hi> where having been narrowly examined by <hi>Richard Walpool,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fugitive, by Order a Jeſuite, of great repute and Authority, he was quickly ſet at liberty, by the means and Interceſſion of that Jeſuite, who began to watch and obſerve him, and perceiving in him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than ordinary of natural parts and abilities, he looked on him as a perſon made for his purpoſe, and a very fit Inſtrument for him to work on.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101373:11"/>
            <p>And becauſe he always found him firm to his Engliſh Religion, he purchaſed for him another priſon, and cauſed him to be put into the <hi>Holy Houſe,</hi> and ſo to be brought to the Inquiſition, and there being perſons on purpoſe ordered to manage him as they ſaw fit, they knew ſo well how to work him, that they quickly got him to be a Catholick; though peradventure, it was not out of any other devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than to get looſe from his Chains, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf free out of priſon. But by what way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it was, to be ſure it could be by none but ſuch as was to be recommended in the Jeſuite. And now having gained this advantage over him, they thought they had a good footing whereby to reach all their further deſigns, and they would not ſuffer him to take any breath, but ſtill kept rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of him down, and by all ſorts of artifice they laboured to fix him faſt in their nets, falling upon the old burden of their uſual ſong, remonſtrating to him the afflictions and tyrannies uſed to the Engliſh Catholicks, who remained ſtill in their Countrey; and much more to thoſe who had forſaken it, and all their eſtates; only that they might enjoy the full freedome of their conſciences: As alſo, as what <hi>Speed</hi> ſays, <hi>upon how few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons the Engliſh State did ſtand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In vit. Eliz. f. <hi>1163.</hi> n. <hi>120.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and how eaſily thoſe props were to be removed, if any devoted would put to their hand.</hi> Squire, <hi>who wanted no wit to perceive whereat he aimed; firſt gave ſome ſlight ſignification, and after a more ſerious proteſtation, that he was the man that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101373:12"/>would ſacrifice himſelf, and his utmoſt ſervice in the cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, that of all theſe miſeries and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> then Earl Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, and afterwards Vice-roy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> was the greateſt Author; that it was abſolutely neceſſary to ſend him packing out of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as alſo out of the world by poiſon; and that he would undertake to put him into a way, to do it without the leaſt hazard to himſelf. <hi>Squire</hi> having pretty glibly ſwallowed this firſt Pill down, which his good ghoſtly father had given him to take, he begins to paſs further, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe alſo to him the taking away of the Queens life, which was as needful to be done; and which would be as pleaſing to the Church, as the ridding the Earl of his: and then he compleated his charm. <hi>It were, no doubt,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>a work meritorious to kill the Earl of</hi> Eſſex; <hi>but alſo there is</hi> unum neceſſarium, <hi>one thing indiſpenſably neceſſary;</hi> and told him openly that he had a greater ſervice for him to do, which would be no leſs acceptable to God than men, and which would not put him into any danger of life, though he ſhould be ſeen doing it, becauſe it was not to be done immediately upon her perſon, nor in her preſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if he would but carefully follow his directions: but however, put it to the worſt, though his enter-prize ſhould not ſucceed accordingly, but that he ſhould be ſound out in it, and taken; yet he aſſured him, <hi>he would only exchange his preſent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101373:12"/>eſtate of life, into that of a glorious Saint and Martyr in Paradiſe, and he hoped he would not think that any hard bargain, to loſe earth to be poſſeſſed of Heaven and Bliſs.</hi> And he purſued him ſo cloſely, that at laſt he overcame him, and made him conſent to his will: but ſeeing that he oft times wavered and ſtartled, he frequently confeſſed him for his further ſtrengthning and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation: remonſtrating to him that he ought not any more to reflect within himſelf, and to deliberate upon the matter; that the bargain was made with his conſcience and him, and now whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was a work good or evil, he was not to diſpute; but without any more to do, to bethink himſelf of his vow: which if he ſhould in the leaſt be failing in, he would be guilty of a crime irreconcileable to God, and he would for certain throw himſelf into the loweſt pit of Hell and damnation: then he alledged to him, and bid h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m ſeriouſly to conſider it, the example of <hi>Jeph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> who thought he was rather obliged, in duty to kill his Daughter, than to break the ſolemn vow which he had made. This poor wretch thus manacled, as I may ſay, and ſetter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Jeſuites Deviliſh perſwaſions, paſſes over to him a moſt firm and inviolable reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whom having once more made to come to a confeſſion, as to the laſt thing which was to conclude this Holy conſpiracy, he gave him his benediction, raiſing him up, and putting his left hand round about his neck, and with the other doing on his face the ſign of the croſs, he mumbled
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101373:13"/>over a few words in Latine, and then ſpake thus to him diſtinctly in Engliſh. <hi>My ſon, God bleſs thee, and eſtabliſh and ſtrengthen thee: be of good courage, I will ingage my Soul for thine, and thou ſhalt have a ſhare in my prayers, dead, or alive.</hi> After he had again imbraced him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the neck, <hi>Squire</hi> took his leave of <hi>Wall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poole,</hi> and within a ſhort time after ſet ſail for <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the inſtruction which the Jeſuite had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, was of a poiſon put into a double blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which alſo then he preſented him with: charging him not to touch it but with thick dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gloves upon his hands, that ſo he may not poiſon and deſtroy himſelf: for it is reported that the vigour of it was ſuch, as neither continuance of time, nor ſubtilty of air was able to check, or un-virtuate the ſtrength. And when the Queen was reſolved to ride abroad, he ſhould prick the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders full of holes, and ſo then rub the poiſon as he preſſed it out, upon the pommel of the Queen's Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle: aſſuring himſelf that the Queen muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity lay her hand on that, and then in all probability at one time or another bringing up her hand to her mouth, or to ſome part of her face, the poiſon would get ſuch acceſs to her, as moſt certainly to be her death: that he muſt alſo do the like to the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> who was making ready to go to <hi>Cadiz,</hi> and had raiſed ſeveral Troops, when <hi>Squire</hi> arrived at <hi>England;</hi> who preſented himſelf to a Privy Counſellour, and being pretty favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101373:13"/>received at his arrival, he was conſulting how to put in execution his helliſh deſign againſt the Queen, before the Earls embarking, into whoſe retinue he was reſolved to put himſelf, if poſſibly he could: thinking that if the poiſon would not do its work under ſome length of time, and it ſhould have its operation during his abſence, he might not be any ways ſuſpected. Upon this reflection he watches all opportunities to effect his deſign; and one day hearing the Queen had a mind to ride a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, he ran preſently to the ſtable yard, where he found the Horſe already Saddled, that ſhe was to ride on; but he pretending to mend ſomething he ſaw amiſs about the Horſe, laid his hand upon the pummel of her Saddle, and bruiſing the Poiſon out of the Bladders, he rubs the pommel with it: exactly following the direction which had been given him by his Father Confeſſour; and as he was buſie about his work, he ſays aloud, and chearfully, <hi>God ſave the Queen,</hi> reiterating thoſe words ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times over. But it pleaſed the Almighty, who had already delivered her from manifold dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to continue ſtill his wonted and wonderful protection to her, keeping her in ſafety under the ſhadow of his wings; for although the ſeaſon was then very hot, being in the month of <hi>July,</hi> and ſo conſequently the veins more open and ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any malignant influences, yet was ſhe unhurt; and as <hi>God ſhut up the mouths of the Lyons that they ſhould not touch</hi> Daniel <hi>the ſervant of the moſt high,</hi> ſo had he ordered that poiſon, otherwiſe ſo ſtrong and powerful, not to have the leaſt vertue which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101373:14"/>was proper to it. She remained well as ever, and it <hi>had no more power over her,</hi> than <hi>Nebuchadnezzars fiery furnace</hi> had over the bodies of thoſe three faithful and famous perſons, <hi>who had not ſo much as a hair of their head ſinged, neither were their coats changed, nor indeed had ſo much as the ſmell of the fire paſſed on them,</hi> for God had ſent his Angel to preſerve them. But for all this, that wicked wretch did not leave off hoping but that it would have its deſigned effect in time. Therefore without any miſtruſt, <hi>Squire</hi> taking the remainder of the poiſon, within ſix days after imbarques; and as the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rl was at Sea, betwixt <hi>Faiel</hi> and Saint <hi>Michaels,</hi> a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dinner time, he rubs the Pommels of a wooden Chair, wherein this Earl did uſually ſit at meals, with the ſame confection. This being done, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that at Supper, the Earl finding himſelf a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle indiſpoſed, <hi>Squire</hi> was cock ſure in his thoughts that he had effectually done his work. But he was alſo deceived herein, for it pleaſed God to preſerve him ſafe, in making the poiſon of no force at all. In the mean time ſome months ſlipped away, and <hi>Wallpool</hi> could hear no news of the death of the Queen: wherefore then beginning to ſuſpect that <hi>Squire</hi> had only abuſed him, he was taking thought how to be revenged on him, and he ſent expreſly an Engliſh-man over, who pretending that he had ſtole away from the Spaniſh Inquiſition, by parcels and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail told them all the conſpiracy, and that he had made his eſcape on purpoſe to give the Queen information of it. Although at the firſt they looked upon this as a trick invented by ſome of <hi>Squire</hi>'s enemies,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101373:14"/>yet it being a buſineſs of ſo high an importance, they judged it a thing not to be deſpiſed. <hi>Squire</hi> was ſent for, and examined, to know the truth of the matter: he at firſt too denies all; but cloſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances being put to him, and his conſcience withal working; he confeſſes the whole buſineſs, and how far he had gone in it, which was impoſſible ever to have been found out but by himſelf, he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving none privy to his Treaſon; and at the Bar he had his ſentence of death paſſed upon him, and was accordingly executed in the year 1598. a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge truly worthy a Jeſuite to take, and yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry miraculous too, that our gracious Queen ſhould not have any intelligence of that Treaſon, but by him who was the firſt deſigner of it. And if <hi>Richeome</hi> would take my counſel, he ſhould put in this miracle too, to help fill up his Book.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
